Greetings from Sweden.
我在瑞典向大家问好
This is Ulf over at Soundtrap from Spotify
我是来自Spotify的Ulf 负责Soundtrap业务
and I'm going to give a talk
下面我将为大家
around some audio latency aspects of the web standards
就web标准和浏览器现状的
and the browser states. slide-2
音频延迟做演讲 slide-2
So let's go to the slide number two
那么我们直接进入
directly and just watch
第二张幻灯片
a small clip showcasing using Soundtrap. 9-p
观看一段使用Soundtrap的演示 9-p
(gentle music) 10-p
（轻柔的音乐） 10-p
(enthusiastic music) 11-p
（热情的音乐） 11-p
Okay.
好的
So, what you saw and heard was me messing about
那么你刚才看到和听到的是我在鼓捣
with the product itself,
产品本身的功能
playing some notes,
弹一些音符
and playback of a project. slide-3
以及某个项目的回播 slide-3
Slide 3
第三张幻灯片
What is Soundtrap then? 18-p
那么什么是Soundtrap呢 18-p
Well, Soundtrap is
Soundtrap其实是
an online collaborative DAW and DAW is,
一个在线协作的DAW平台
as you may know,
DAW指的是
a Digital Audio Workstation. 22-p
数字音频工作站 22-p
And,
而且
this means that we have features such as multi-track
这意味着我们有多轨编辑
with a media recording and editing.
媒体录制和音乐编辑等功能
We have software instruments,
我们有虚拟乐器
we have audio effects, reverbs, filters,
我们有音频效果 混响 过滤器
guitar, automation and so on.
吉他音箱模拟等等
And we implement all of this through heavy use
我们使用了繁多的web标准来实现其功能
of web standards such as Web Audio, Web media,
如Web Audio Web MIDI
media recorder, media stream
以及MediaRecorder MediaStream
and so on and so forth slide-4
等等诸如此类 slide-4
Slide 4 33-p
第四张幻灯片 33-p
But as I mentioned that we focusing here today on aspects of
但正如我所说 我们今天在这里集中讨论
audio latency,
音频延迟方面
and
而且
it is essential to many of our use cases of Soundtrap. 37-p
它对Soundtrap的许多用例至关重要 37-p
Specifically here, we want to mention
我们这里要特别提一下
the case of monitoring,
监听音频的场景
and that is
也就是你所录制的内容的即时反馈
So you would record from mic, process stuff in web audio and
也就是你用麦克风录音 在Web Audio中处理
play back through your speaker
然后通过你的扬声器进行回放 46-p
A good example of that is a guitarist that uses the
例如吉他演奏者可以把DAW平台
DAW as a substitute really for
用作硬件的
the hardware,
替代品
as pedals and amplifiers. 50-p
作为踏板和放大器 50-p
And they play along
他们要跟着耳返
with what they hear.
同时演奏
I mean, it matters what the output,
那么音频输出
resulting output is,
最终输出的结果就很重要
like, how hard should I string to get this kind of tone
例如我需要如何调弦才能产生这种音色
in my repo, whatever. 56-p
或者什么其他效果 56-p
And another example is the key
另一个例子是键盘演奏者
that is playing using the DAW
使用DAW平台
as a software instrument essentially. And
作为虚拟乐器进行演奏
if there's a substantial lag from pressing a key to
如果从按键到听到音符有很大的延迟
hearing it the note you get for an orphan.
你就会被打断
Additionally you play alone
除此之外 你还可以
every already existing track or set of tracks. slide-5
在现有的轨道或一组轨道上进行演奏 slide-5
Slide 5 64-p
第五张幻灯片 64-p
Well,
那么目前的现状是怎样的呢
I mean, we can see something like 30ms best case
在最佳情况下 我们可以做到
round-trip latency, which is
30毫秒的往返延迟
passable for monitoring purposes, but not great.
对于音频监听差强人意 但还不算优秀
And then it's, in some cases it's not sufficient
我们认为在某些情况下 延迟还不够低
and we'd like to get this much lowered to be able to compete
说真的 我们希望能把它降得更低
with the native offerings. Really. 74-p
能够达到原生硬件的水平 74-p
I mean, 10ms is a good target, that really is decent. slide-6
要是能达到10毫秒这样的水平就很不错了 slide-6
The second problem
在我们的用例中
that we have in our use case that is
遇到的第二个问题
maybe not immediately clear obvious to people is
也许对大家来说并不是特别显眼
you record several things in succession
就是你连续记录了几段音乐
and you need to align them.
然后你需要将它们对齐
(chuckles)
（轻笑）
Sounds obvious, but it is trickier than you might think.
听上去理所当然 但比你想象的要棘手
That we call recording latency compensation.
这就是我们所说的录音延时补偿
There are probably other words for it as well. 84-p
可能有别的称呼 84-p
In order to show that you need two things really,
为了实现这一点 你需要两方面的数据
you need
你需要知道
what is the round-trip latency.
往返的延迟是多少
You need to know that actually, actual latency.
你需要知道实际的延迟是多少
And you need to know when the data arrived
你还需要知道数据是在什么时候
towards your storage or stream, or what have you.
输入至你的存储或流之类的
To be able to when you play them back later,
为了能够在之后回放时
the data that ou aggregated, the relative alignment of
你所汇总的数据 你所听到的
what you heard and what you produced should be retained. slide-7
和你所演奏的对齐相对值应该被保留下来 slide-7
Slide 7 95-p
第七张幻灯片 95-p
And what do we mean by roundtrip latency? Well,
那我们所说的往返延迟是什么意思呢
that is several things combined. It's the input latency,
其实是几方面的组合 包括了输入延迟
it's the processing latency and it's the output latency.
处理延迟以及输出延迟
And that's not very surprising, I guess.
当然这也是意料之中的
But we'll get back to why it gets complicated. 100-p
但我们稍后再来谈它为什么会那么复杂 100-p
Then what if we have the wrong information or
如果我们得到的是错误信息
really no information,
或者一点信息也没有
we can't do a good job, we would have misaligned playback,
那么录制的音频就会错位
and obviously we do something,
当然我们也不是束手无策
but that involves educated guesswork and that's not ideal.
但那就涉及到高难度推测 而这并不理想
We'd like to explicitly know what the latencies are that are
我们想准确地知道其中涉及的延迟
involved here. 107-p
到底是多少 107-p
I mean, if not doing anything, the user would have to
如果什么也不做 用户将不得不手动对齐
manually align,
这远非理想的用户体验 slide-8
Slide 8. 111-p
第八张幻灯片 111-p
The point is
问题是
that both the input and output paths
输入和输出路径
have many pieces or steps involved.
都涉及到许多环节或步骤
And these things look differently on different audio stacks
而这些东西在不同的音频栈
and/or operating systems and what have you. 116-p
和/或操作系统中看起来是不同的 116-p
The latencies introduced by these steps are
这些步骤引入的延迟
also vastly different,
也大相径庭
and not all of them,
而且并不是所有的步骤
allow knowing this, so naturally strive for
都能够获取其中的延迟 所以自然要尽量
picking technical solutions data that allow this.
挑选能够获取的技术方案
To allow knowing this, sorry, I should say. 122-p
抱歉 是能够获取延迟的方案 122-p
It's not just the
不仅仅是
path towards the browser or from the browser thought
输入浏览器的路径或来自浏览器的路径
may have hidden latencies. It could also be
可能有隐藏的延迟 如果你不够谨慎
within the browser itself if you're not careful.
浏览器本身也可能存在延迟
And here we try to illustrate this with,
我们尝试在这里用
well,
那个
bear with us.
请稍等
We pretend that the media stream track setting latency
我们假设MediaStreamTrack设置的latency属性
is a good indication of the input path latency.
是输入路径延迟的一项明显指标
Might not be, but we can return to that. 133-p
可能不是 但我们回过头再来说 133-p
Anyway, so we operate in the Web Audio world.
总之 我们是在Web Audio中操作
So that means that we take
因此这意味着我们可以
that number from the setting,
从设置中得到这个数字
and then we can see it
然后我们可以看到
probably isn't the same once you sort of
一旦你进入Web Audio内
stepped into the Web Audio world,
这一数字可能就不一样了
because there's a node there as well,
因为那里也有一个节点
which may or may not do any additional buffering and that
它可能会也可能不会做任何额外的缓冲
additional buffering or latency is not exposed anywhere. 142-p
而额外的缓冲或延迟信息没有办法获取 142-p
But it ought to be, otherwise
但应该让我们获取
we don't have good
否则我们就无法得到
accurate numbers. slide-9
准确的数字了 slide-9
Slide 9 146-p
第九张幻灯片 146-p
For completeness,
为了完整阐述这个问题
I'll just talk a little bit about the output
我还是再谈一下输出步骤
and the processing steps. 149-p
和处理步骤 149-p
And
而且它有一定的额大小或块大小
or which is separate quantum sum.
或者是单独的额总和
That latency also needs to be known and tracked somewhere. 153-p
这个延迟也需要在某个地方获取和跟踪 153-p
And likewise for the input, the output latencies
同样地 和输入延迟一样
also need to be exposed somehow somewhere. 155-p
输出延迟也需要以某种方式获取 155-p
If you take a closer look at the Web Audio context property
如果你仔细看看Web Audio中的
outputLatency, it does seem to indicate that is
outputLatency属性 它似乎的确表示了
the block size as well as the output path combined,
块大小以及输出路径延迟之和
but it's not immediately clear. slide-10
但它并没有明确指出这一点 slide-10
Slide 10 160-p
第十张幻灯片 160-p
The other aspect to get
要正确实现延迟补偿的另一个方面
compensation done correctly is knowing accurately
是准确了解数据到达的时机
when your data arrived. As I mentioned earlier.
正如我之前提到的
It can be done in
它可以通过各种方式实现
not really.
但是其实
There's no brilliant way to do it. 167-p
没有什么高明的方法可以做到这一点 167-p
Traditionally. We've been using the media recorder
传统上 我们一直在使用MediaRecorder
and
而且
it's nice in many ways,
它在很多方面都很优秀
because that allows you to sort of encode the file
因为它基本上能够让你实时编码
and things like that. 172-p
诸如此类的 172-p
But there's no,
但是
as far as we can see spec-wise or guarantees that
就我们所看到的规格而言
when you start it, it's going to start
它不能保证当你启动它时 它就马上启动
And even if it were you're still going to be like a
即使能做到这一点 你仍然会
quantum material of your sample, but then it started,
与你的采样相差一两个单位 然后它再启动
you get the idea. 179-p
你应该明白我的意思 179-p
And I mean, a second option could be like,
第二个选择可以是
you do something custom based on the worklet.
你在Worklet的基础上做一些自定义的东西
You know everything then,
这样你就能获取所有信息
but then you have to do everything as well.
但你也必须从零实现所有功能
And even if using something like WebCodecs,
即使是用像WebCodecs这样的东西
it seems that you still have to packetize
你可能还是得把它打包成一个容器格式
into like a container from it, which is, I mean,
但是这种方式吧
it can be done, but it's not ideal. slide-11
可以实现 但这并不理想 slide-11
Slide 11 188-p
第十一张幻灯片 188-p
To conclude the stock,
这里总结一下演讲
first off the input and output latency are
首先 输入和输出的延迟
maybe
可能是
spec-ed.
规范的
It's not clear that they are the full parts that we
目前还不清楚它们是否符合我们预想中的
intend to hear. 194-p
全路径 194-p
And then specifically,
然后具体来说
we have some thoughts around the MediaStreamSourceNode
我们对MediaStreamSourceNode接口有一些想法
and similar translation pieces between different
以及在不同音频标准之间实现转换
standards, like any additional latency needs to be exposed. 198-p
比如任何额外的延迟信息都需要获取 198-p
And then, there seems to be an opportunity to
其次 似乎有那么一个可能
spice up the media stream recorder,
可以增强MediaStreamRecorder
to get accurate timing information by some callback or
通过回调或其他方式获得准确的时间信息 202-p
Finally, the WebCodecs API
最后 WebCodecs很棒 但是
there's something missing in the sense that we
我们还缺少
don't have packetization, or containerization
打包化 或者说容器化
or whatever the correct term would be. 207-p
或者有什么其他的叫法 207-p
And finally, of course,
最后 当然
we just want to encourage all the implementers to get the
我们只是想鼓励所有的实现者
input and output latencies
把输入和输出的延迟
low obviously,
降低
and pick drivers that allows exposing the information
并选择允许获取信息的驱动程序
because we need it
毕竟工欲善其事
to do a good job. slide-12
必先利其器 slide-12
Thank you. That's all for us.
谢谢大家 我们的演讲就到这里
And see you at the discussions.
我们研讨会上见